A Guide to the William Faulkner Collection,
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
William Faulkner Collection 1935-1963
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6271-ax
This collection consists of 88 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the Library's microfilms of the William Faulkner manuscripts in its custody; the microfilm may be consulted by any interested party, and it will be lent through the interlibrary loan system. Materials are constantly added. Long-term loans may be arranged. Use of the microfilm will be restricted to the premises of the borrowing library. No loans will be made to individuals. Researchers should enquire of the Manuscripts Division concerning availability of microfilm of manuscripts that are pertinent to their work. Most of the literary manuscripts in our collections written by Faulkner, both holograph and typescript, have also been published in facsimile in William Faulkner Manuscripts, 25 vols (New York: Garland, 1986-87).
By the terms of the agreement by which the William Faulkner Foundation transferred the original manuscripts to the University, access to the original manuscripts is restricted (to ensure the survival of the physically-delicate originals) to doctoral candidates at the dissertation stage of their programs, and to certain mature scholars and critics. But even these researchers must demonstrate need to see the originals that goes beyond the requirements of most routine research. A doctoral candidate at the dissertation stage, or other qualified researcher who believes that his or her work requires access to the originals must correspond with the Curator of Manuscripts prior to arrival at the Library to obtain permission for access.
No microfilm, electrostatic, or other types of copies may be made of materials written by William Faulkner that are in our William Faulkner Collections. Other materials in the collections may be copied subject to the normal rules of the Library established under the conditions of the Copyright Act. All copying is performed by the Printing Services Department of the University.
Acquisition Information
Collected by Linton R. Massey and Presented to the Rare Book Department.
Scope and Content Information
Microfilm copies of theses and dissertations on William Faulkner.
Contents List
- "William Faulkner And The Contemporary Social Scene" 1952
  Reel 1, by Jackson W. Heimer, M.A. Thesis, University of Kentucky
- "William Faulkner: His Characterization And Use Of Women" 1959
  Reel 1, by Kaye Elizabeth Bache, M.A. Thesis, University of Colorado,
- " A Fable By William Faulkner: Reality Or Ruse" 1958
  Reel 1, by Emmy Lou Dinda, Honors Paper, Valparaiso University,
- "The Revisions Of William Faulkner's Go Down, Moses" 1955
  Reel 1, by Norma Ridley, M.A. Thesis, University of Arkansas,
- "Racial Relations In The Fiction Of William Faulkner: A Study Of Meaning" 1951
  Reel 1, by Dennis M. Jones, M.A. Thesis, State University of Iowa,
- "A Consideration Of The Contrasting Opinions Of William Faulkner's Attitude Toward The Negro" 1951
  Reel 1, by William Kausch Campbell, M.A. Thesis, State University of Iowa,
- "William Faulkner: The Yoknapatawpha Novels And The Nobel Prize Speech" 1954
  Reel 1, by Jun Fulkerson Todd, M.A. Thesis, Southern Illinois University,
- "Morality In William Faulkner's Novels" 1954
  Reel 1, by Charles Thomas Vernon, M.A. Thesis, Drake University,
- "A Comparative Study Of Hawthorne And Faulkner" 1960
  Reel 1, by Evelyn Roddey Taylor, M.A. Thesis, Drake University,
- "A Comparative Analysis Of The Waste Land Theme In T. S. Eliot And William Faulkner" 1960
  Reel 1, by Stuart L. Burns, M.A. Thesis, Drake University,
- "William Faulkner: A Study Of His Development As A Novelist" 1950
  Reel 1, by William Anthony Scott, M.A. Thesis, University of Arizona,
- "William Faulkner: A Critical Estimate" 1935
  Reel 2, by James Walter Thetford, M.A. Thesis, Vanderbilt University,
- "The Growing Optimism Of William Faulkner" 1953
  Reel 2, by Joseph Hoyt Reynolds, Jr., M.A. Thesis, Vanderbilt University,
- "William Faulkner And The Old Southwestern Yarnspinners" 1954
  Reel 2, by John McDonald, M.A. Thesis, University of Miami,
- "A View Of Faulkner's Women" 1959
  Reel 2, by Lewis J. Hilliard, M.A. Thesis, Southern Illinois University,
- "The Theme In Faulkner's Light In August: An Approach Through Polarity" 1957
  Reel 2, by David Lowell Frazier, M.A. Thesis, Indiana University,
- "Decadence In The 'Mystic' Novels Of William Faulkner" 1951
  Reel 2, by [Sarah H. Youngblood], M.A. Thesis, University of Oklahoma,
- "Emerson And Faulkner: Some Problems Of The Romantic Artist In America" 1958
  Reel 2, by Ted Larry Pebworth, M.A. Thesis, Tulane University,
- "William Faulkner's Fiction" 1952
  Reel 2, by Mary Helen Rohrberger, M.A. Thesis, Tulane University,
- "Christ Figures In The Novels Of William Faulkner" 1959
  Reel 3, by Joyce Bellomy, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- " The Sound And The Fury And As I Lay Dying: A Comparison" 1959
  Reel 3, by Edward Robert Simmer, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "The Image Of The 'Waste Land' In The Works Of William Faulkner" 1959
  Reel 3, by Miriam M. Roshwald, M.A. Thesis, University of Minnesota,
- "Sin And Redemption In Faulkner" 1955
  Reel 3, by Joe Drake Gilliland, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "Two William Faulkners: A Study In Contrasts" 1941
  Reel 3, by Mary Elizabeth Watts, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "William Faulkner's Yoknapatawpha Characters" 1952
  Reel 3, by William Joseph Wiley, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "The Narrative Technique Of William Faulkner" 1947
  Reel 3, by James Allen Hill, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "William Faulkner And Ivan Bunin: Their Worlds" 1952
  Reel 3, by Peggy Irene Haskel, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "William Faulkner's Light In August: A Critical Analysis" 1960
  Reel 3, by Paul Witherington, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "Anderson, Hemingway, Faulkner: Three Studies Of Mytho- Symbolism In American Literature" 1947
  Reel 4, by Don DeVere Walker, M.A. Thesis, University of Utah,
- "An Interpretation Of William Faulkner Based On A Study Of His Prose Fiction" 1940
  Reel 4, by Lyle Wagstaff, M.A. Thesis, University of Utah,
- "Time And Structure In The Novels Of William Faulkner" 1954
  Reel 4, by Peter Swiggart, Ph.D. Dissertation, Yale University,
- "Faulkner's Dramatic Psychology" 1954
  Reel 4, by Bruce Olson, M.A. Thesis, Indiana University,
- "Sprachstil Und Weltbild Bei William Faulkner" 1958
  Reel 4, by Lore Nolting-Hauff, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Freiburg,
- "A Psychoanalytical Consideration Of The Abnormal Characters In The Novels Of William Faulkner" 1937
  Reel 4, by John Raymond Butterworth, M.A. Thesis, University of Southern California,
- "Faulkner's Light In August: A Symbolic Reading" 1955
  Reel 5, by John William Matheson, M.A. Thesis, University of Washington,
- "William Faulkner: A Study In Technique" 1948
  Reel 5, by Rex Odell Matthews, M.A. Thesis, University of Washington,
- "The Negro In The Fiction Of William Faulkner" 1953
  Reel 5, by Agnes Louise Moreland, M.A. Thesis, University of Washington,
- "A Study Of The 'Incest Theme' In Two Works Of William Faulkner: The Sound And The Fury And Absalom, Absalom!" 1954
  Reel 5, by Idelle Sullens, M.A. Thesis, University of Washington,
- "Harmony In Discord: A Study Of Faulkner's Light In August" 1954
  Reel 5, by William J. Park, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "The World And Nature In Some Typical Stories Of William Faulkner" 1955
  Reel 5, by Carolyn E. Nagy, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "The Shape Of Morality In The Novels Of William Faulkner" 1954
  Reel 5, by Arnold Fisher, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "William Faulkner: The Double Legend" 1952
  Reel 5, by Thomas A. Dardis, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "William Faulkner And The Tragic Ritual" 1951
  Reel 5, by Ernest G. Griffin, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "Time And Technique In The Sound And The Fury" 1952
  Reel 5, by Edwy B. Lee, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "William Faulkner: Character As Theme And Structure" 1952
  Reel 6, by Eugene J. Hall, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "William Faulkner: The Symbolic Action Of Sin And Redemption" 1952
  Reel 6, by Lawrence S. Dembo, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "Early Faulkner Criticism" 1952
  Reel 6, by William Joseph Nemser, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- The Religion Of William Faulkner: An Inquiry Into The Calvinist Mind" 1953
  Reel 6, by Jules Newman, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "The Hour Before The Dawn: A Study Of William Faulkner's Treatment Of The Negro" 1954
  Reel 6, by Yvonne Silverman, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "William Faulkner's Proper Study: An Essay On The Positive Directive In Faulkner's Writing" 1952
  Reel 6, by Edward A. Martin, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "William Faulkner And The Changing Social Structure Of The South" 1951
  Reel 6, by George Leon Groman, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "Yoknapatawpha And The Natchez Trace: A Study Of Regional Influences Of William Faulkner And Eudora Welty" 1955
  Reel 6, by Richard A. Armstrong, M.A. Thesis, Columbia University,
- "Faulkner's Fondness For Modern French Technique" 1953
  Reel 7, by M. Douglas Swearingen Ehrlich, M.A. Thesis, University of South Carolina,
- "The 'Prufrock' Theme In The Novels Of William Faulkner" 1948
  Reel 7, by Ruth Gasser Fourier, M.A. Thesis, University of South Carolina,
- "The Theme Of Rapacity In Selected Novels Of William Faulkner" 1959
  Reel 7, by Ian Jackson, M.A. Thesis, University of South Carolina,
- "The Negro Problem In William Faulkner's Yoknapatawpha Series" 1956
  Reel 7, by Irwin Weldon Coleman, Jr., M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "Faulkner's The Sound And The Fury" 1958
  Reel 7, by Patsy Ann Hall, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "The Decline Of Faulkner's Art"
  Reel 7, by Leila Downs Clark Wynn, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "The Negro In The Prose Of William Faulkner"
  Reel 7, by John M. Nesselhof, M.A. Thesis, University of Kansas
- "The Road To William Faulkner: A Reading Of Southern Fiction" 1957
  Reel 8, by Leonard Mikules, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of California-Los Angeles,
- "William Faulkner And The Humor Of The Old Southwest" 1952
  Reel 8, by Bettye Field, M.A. Thesis, Vanderbilt University,
- "Social Attitudes In Five Contemporary Southern Novelists: Erskine Caldwell, William Faulkner, Ellen Glasgow, Caroline Gordon, And T. S. Stribling" 1945
  Reel 8, by Althea Catherine Cater, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Michigan,
- "An Encyclopedia Of Characters In The Novels Of William Faulkner" 1955
  Reel 8, by Mona Margaret Melrose, M.A. Thesis, University of Hawaii,
- " These Thirteen: The Structure Of The Yoknapatawpha Series" 1957
  Reel 8, by Thomas Sherman, M.A. Thesis, Emory University,
- "William Faulkner's Absalom, Absalom!" 1959
  Reel 9, by Robert Hilton Knox III, Ph.D. Dissertation, Harvard University,
- "William Faulkner: Studies In [For And ] 1952
  Reel 9, by Earl Edwin Zink, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Washington,
- "Das Land Und Die Menschen In William Faulkner's Erzahlenden Werken" 1953
  Reel 9, by Gerald Hintegegger, Ph.D. Dissertation, Karl-franzens-Universitat in Graz,
- "The Southern Legend In The Yoknapatawpha Fiction Of William Faulkner" 1950
  Reel 9, by T. Y. Greet, M.A. Thesis, University of North Carolina,
- "Some Aspects Of The Treatment Of Negro Characters By Five Representative American Novelists: Cooper, Melville, Tourgee, Glasgow, Faulkner" 1952
  Reel 10, by Charles Hampton Nilon, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Wisconsin,
- "The Novels Of William Faulkner: Patterns Of Perspective" 1953
  Reel 10, by Olga Westland Vickery, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Wisconsin,
- "The Concept Of Love In The Novels Of William Faulkner" 1955
  Reel 11, by Lonnie Dean Hefner, M.A. Thesis, University of Texas,
- "William Faulkner And The Negro" 1955
  Reel 11, by William Clark Doster, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Florida,
- "A Theological Critique Of The Interpretation Of Man In The Fiction And Drama Of William Faulkner, Ernest Hemingway, Jean-Paul Sartre, And Albert Camus" 1953
  Reel 11, by Edwin A. Penick, Jr., Ph.D. Dissertation, Yale University,
- "Thematik, Symbolik, Und Technik In Werk Der William Faulkners" 1950
  Reel 11, by Edgar Lohner, Ph.D. Dissertation, Reinischen Friedrich-Wilhems-Universitat su Boan,
- "Study Of William Faulkner's Moral Philosophy" 1958
  Reel 12, by James Owen Williams, M.A. Thesis, University of Denver,
- "The Narrative Technique Of William Faulkner In The Yoknapatawpha Cycle" 1960
  Reel 12, by Cecil Clark Chism, M.A. Thesis, University of Missouri,
- "Gothic Devices Used As Symbols In The Works Of William Faulkner" 1960
  Reel 12, by Donald Michael Michie, M.A. Thesis, University of Missouri,
- "The World Of William Faulkner" 1951
  Reel 12, by Ward L. Miner, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Pennsylvania,
- "William Faulkner: Past To Self-Discovery: A Study Of His Life And Work Through Sartoris(1929)" 1963
  Reel 12, by Harold Edward Richardson, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Southern California,
- "A Combination O The Returned Veteran Theme In William Gilmore Simm's Woodcraft And William Faulkner's Soldier's Pay" 1957
  Reel 13, by Jesse Cecil Gatlin, Jr., M.A. Thesis, University of North Carolina,
- "Faulkner's Women In The Structure Of His Yoknapatawpha World, 1929-1936" 1959
  Reel 13, by Nancy McFadden, M.A. Thesis, University of North Carolina,
- "The Main Trends In The Criticism Of William Faulkner" 1957
  Reel 13, by Irene Lynn Sleeth, MS Thesis, University of North Carolina,,
- "William Faulkner's Novels Of Yoknapatawpha County" 1942
  Reel 13, by William W. Pearson, Honors Essay, [University of North Carolina],
- "William Faulkner And The Gothic Tradition" 1958
  Reel 13, by Ruth Ann Voth, M.A. Thesis, University of Maryland,
- "The Focus Of William Faulkner's Absalom, Absalom!" 1959
  Reel 13, by Arlyn Bruccoli, M.A. Thesis (2316), University of Virginia,
- "The Theme Of Victory Through Defeat In Works By Faulkner, Steinbeck, And Hemingway" 1959
  Reel 13, by Richard Henry Wilde Dillard, M.A. Thesis (2363), University of Virginia,
- "The Fire And The Hearth/ Conflict And Affirmation In William Faulkner" 1954
  Reel 13, by Robert Wayne Caswell, M.A. Thesis, University of Vermont,
- "William Faulkner's Perception Of Reality" 1954
  Reel 13, by Ronald Hafter, M.A. Thesis, University of Vermont,